A Finding Aid to the Daniel Varney Thompson Papers, 1848-1979, bulk 1923-1979, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Writings, 1907-1970s; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 6-9; 2.85 linear ft.)
  - By Daniel Varney Thompson - Personal and Professional, 1921-1966; 4.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Art Notes, Index to Medieval Manuscripts on Craftsmanship (arranged by library), 1935; Archival Resource Key; (2 card files) (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    - Art Notes, Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Art Writings, 1935-1937, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
    - Diary, Trip to India (typescript copy), 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Diary and Address Book, 1933-1934; Archival Resource Key; (1 vol. disbound) (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Poems, 1928-1929, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Scientific and Technical Notebooks, 1926-1949; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 22-25)
    - Scientific and Technical Notebooks, 1950-1957, undated; Archival Resource Key; (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - Scientific and Technical Notes, 1956-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
    - Scientific and Technical Writings, 1937-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Student Notes (art history graduate courses), 1924-1925; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - Student Papers (English courses), 1921-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Translation, Diversarium vilium schedula by Theophilus Presbyter, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Translation, Il libro dell'arte by Cennino Cennini, circa 1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Translation, Secretum Philosophorum, 1934; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 15-17)
    - Translation, Various Writings concerning Red and Purple Dyes from Animal Sources, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - By Daniel Varney Thompson - Food and Garden, 1960s-1970s; 4.2; Archival Resource Key
    Thompson's food and garden writings consist of manuscripts, drafts and notes for articles and columns, and for a book-length compilation of these writings.
    - Articles and Columns, A-Z, by title, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key; (6 folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
    - Articles and Columns, Untitled, 1960s-1970s, undated; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 7-10)
    - Articles and Columns, Fragments, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Book, Good Food, Green Gardens and Red and White Wines, 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
    - Columns, "Food and Garden Gossip,", 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
    - Columns, "Foodmanship,", 1969-1971, undated; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 16-20)
    - Columns, "Garden Gossip,", 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 21-22)
    - Columns, "Pleasures of Food and Garden,", 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Columns, "The Second Glass,", 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Columns, Unidentified [possibly "Garden Gossip" or column for Horticulture], 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - By Other Authors, 1907-1967; 4.3; Archival Resource Key
    Writings by other authors include diaries of Thompson's mother and wife and a music score by his brother, Randall Thompson.
    - Saint-Ange, Mme. E. "introduction" (to a cookbook), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Thompson, Cecile de Luze. Diary, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Thompson, Cecile de Luze. Notes on Weaving Patterns (with diagrams), 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Thompson, Grace R. Diary [typescript copy], summer 1907 and summer 1908; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Thompson, Randall. "Say Ye to the Righteous" (music score inscribed to Dan and Cecily), 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Trotta, Geri. "Buenos Aires: Europe I South America,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Artwork, 1923-1934; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; (Box 9, OV package 13; 5 folders)
  This series includes drawings, prints, watercolors, and an oil painting. A small number of drawings, prints and a sketchbook containing pencil sketches and watercolors are by Daniel V. Thompson.
  Artwork is arranged alphabetically by artist.
  - McKean, Mary Sargent. Drawing and Watercolors, 1934, undated; Archival Resource Key; (see also: OV 13) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Thompson, Daniel Varney. Drawings and Prints, 1923, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Thompson, Daniel Varney. Sketchbook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Winslow, Henry. Print, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - McKean, Mary Sargent [signed Sargent]. Oil Painting, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13)
- Printed Material, 1917-1979; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; (Box 9; 0.75 linear ft.)
  Items of particular interest are concert programs and articles about/mentioning noted American composer Randall Thompson, the older brother of Daniel Varney Thompson, and material concerning Daniel Varney Thompson and the Thompson Family. Also included is Le memorie di un pittore di quadric antichi, a book by Inicio Federico Joni under whom Thompson studied medieval and Renaissance painting techniques while in Italy in 1923.
  A significant amount of additional printed material can be found in the Subject Files (Series 3).
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries. Printed material is categorized by record type with each folder arranged chronologically.
  6.1: By Daniel Varney Thompson, 1926-1971
  6.2: By Other Authors, 1917-1979
  - By Daniel Varney Thompson, 1926-1971; 6.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Articles, 1926-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Book Reviews, 1933, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Letters to Editors, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous Items, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Poem, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - By Other Authors, 1924-1974; 6.2; Archival Resource Key
    - About/Mentioning Daniel Varney Thompson, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - Articles, 1924-1967, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Biographical Notes, circa 1950-1979, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Letterheads and Business Cards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Membership Lists, 1936-1964, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - Reviews and Advertisements of Books by Thompson, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - About/Mentioning Randall Thompson, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - Articles, 1939-1974, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Concert Programs, 1939-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - About/Mentioning Thompson Family, 1926-1970, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Articles, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - Art, History Medieval Studies, Science and Technology, 1936-1968, undated; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 9, Folder 25-28)
      - Food and Garden, 1963-1967, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 29)
      - Miscellaneous Subjects, 1962-1973, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Books, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - L'arte della seta in Firenze by Girolamo Gargiolli (photocopy), undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 31)
      - The Göttingen Model Book, edited by Helmut Lehmann-Haupt (photocopy), 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 32)
      - Die Herstellung des Blattmetalls in Altertum und Neuzeit by Wilhelm Theobald, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 33)
      - Le memorie di un pittore di quadric antichi by Inicio Federico Joni, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Items, 1935-1964, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Periodicals - Mathematical Pie (Nos. 1-53), 1950-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Printing Samples (Carl Purington Rollins, Daniel Varney Thompson, and others), 1917-1955, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 37)
- Photographs, circa 1900-1972; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; (Box 10; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Photographs are of artwork, people, places and miscellaneous subjects. The majority of photographs of people are of Daniel V. Thompson and family members. Other individuals portrayed are Edward Forbes with colleagues and family at Villa Curonia, Shaw and Margaret Sargent McKean, and a number of unidentified people. Some Subject Files (Series 3) also include photographs.
  The series is arranged as 5 subseries. Images of artwork are arranged by artist.
  7.1: Artwork, 1906-circa 1941
  7.2: People, circa 1900-1969
  7.3: Places, 1923-1972
  7.4: Miscellaneous Subjects, 1929-1969
  7.5: Negative and Transparency, undated
  - Artwork, 1906-circa 1941; 7.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Greaves, T. A., undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Lyon, Robert, circa 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - McKean, Margaret Sargent, 1937, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Taylor, Edwin C., 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Thompson, Daniel Varney, Jr., circa 1939, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified, 1906-1925, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - People, circa 1900-1969; 7.2; Archival Resource Key
    - Thompson, Cecile de Luze Simonds, 1903-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Thompson, Daniel Varney, Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
      - Portraits, 1903-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - With Cecile and their Children, 1931-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - With Colleagues and Friends, 1919-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Family, Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
      - Thompson Family (group shots with and without Daniel Varney Thompson), 1900-circa 1938, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Thompson, Daniel Varney, Sr. [father], 19th century; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - Thompson, Frederick Lincoln [uncle], circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Thompson, John Ireland [son] and Anthea [daughter], 1939-circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - Thompson, William Ladd [relationship unknown], undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Varney, D. A. [probably uncle or grandfather], 19th century; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Friends, Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
      - Forbes, Edward and Margaret with Others (at Villa Curonia, Florence), 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - McKean, Margaret Sargent, Shaw, and Family, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 18)
      - Other Individuals, 1906-1969, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Places, 1923-1972; 7.3; Archival Resource Key
    - China, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Gardens, 1956-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Greenhouses, 1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Houses, 1964, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Italy, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Storeroom, Daniel Varney, Ltd., 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Unidentified (landscapes; buildings), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects, 1929-1969; 7.4; Archival Resource Key
    - Architectural Models of Yale University Art Gallery (proposed extension), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Automobiles, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Consulting Projects, circa 1940s, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Dogs, 1929-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Flowers, 1966-1969, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Scientific Data, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Negative and Transparency, undated; 7.5; Archival Resource Key
    - Negative (Artwork by Margaret Sargent McKean), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Color Transparency (Consulting Project), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 34)